Hello and welcome to our lecture on the
CDC 6504 architecture. So as you'll soon
see this is a blend of two names so that I can
avoid confusion with the actual processor that
you're simulating. So the processor that we're
simulating is the MOSS technology 6502. It is
there are many microprocessors that have deep
historical significance. The 6502 is a very
significant processor in terms of the history
of CPU architecture and its evolution. It was
launched in 1975 and the key to it was low
cost of manufacturer. It was simple. It only
had 4,000 transistors. Remember the Intel 4004
had 2,300 transistors. This ran into megahertz
and they kept the price low at $25. So it it just
allowed a whole series of hobbyist computers like
the Apple 1, that was a hobbyist computer. And
so it sort of just opened up a whole bunch of
things. And and so the problem is is that
if I named my emulator the 6502 emulator,
it would get lost in all of the confusion. So I
changed it to the CDC 6504 to pay homage to the
first computer that I ever used in the 1970s. from
Control Data Corporation. It I learned FORTRAN on
it. I learned assembly language on it. I learned
machine language on it. And I have a picture here
of a running version of this computer at the
Living Computer Museum in Seattle, Washington
that sadly is now closed after Paul Allen passed
away. But I have a video that I will share with
you. Um that is a video of a running CDC 6500
from a couple of years ago. I further was lucky
to meet an important influence in the CDC6500
history, Nicholas Wirth. He invented Pascal. I
used Pascal. I I supported the Pascal compiler.
It was a really important part of my own sort of
education was to build compilers. And so I'm going
to show you an artifact from that time period. So,
this is from I don't know if you can see it. Let's
see if you can see it here. This is from Yeah,
there you go. 1980. This was a one-year project in
computer science where I This is This is assembly
language from the CD6500. This is a compiler and
an optimizer. And so, it was written in FORTRAN,
right? These are line printers. Uh let's see if
I can find something interesting to show you.
um you know with all kinds of documentation and
so we wrote all this stuff uh in 1979 and 1980 it
was a two student project and I have kept it for
all this time right there we go okay so that's an
artifact from the CDC 6500 and again I named a CDC
6504 just so I had something to search on. So this
is the architecture of the CDC 6504 and the first
thing you have to understand is the registers and
when you start using this interactively online
you'll be reading these registers. So the most
important register the what next register is the
program counter also known as the PC as we've seen
in some earlier lectures there's the current
instruction register which is important and it
often is not shown on architecture diagrams even
though how it's very important the accumulator.
So the CDC6504 and the 6502 is an accumulator
based system and that's sort of like they have
one single most powerful register and that is
the accumulator. As you do operations, they set
flags after every operation so that you can do if
tests. So was the last result zero? Was the last
result negative? It has two more registers that
are a little less powerful than the accumulator
called the X and Y registers. And on the emulator
itself that I've built, it shows the instructions
in base 2, which makes it easier to decode. And
the data memory will be shown in hex given that
most of the time we're just going to be putting
characters into the data memory. So we program
the CDC 6504 in machine language. And so there's
some really good documentation uh that is that I
built with the help of AI. So this is a language
for the clear instruction, clear x, increment x,
etc., etc. So we'll we'll cover these in much
more detail. So let's start right away with
our first program. So you can kind of go back.
So our program is going to compute 1 + 1 = 2 in
the x register. So the PC tells the system where
to retrieve the next instruction from. So when
the program when the computer starts before we
start it running, the PC starts at zero. And so
the first instruction is 1 1 1 0 0 1 0 which is
clearing the X register. Now the system starts
with zeros in there, but it's probably smart
just to clear it anywhere anyway. Then it has an
two increment instructions and then it has an all
zeros instruction which says stop. Okay, so let's
walk this through. So when the first execution
of the first instruction is done, well that sets
the X register to zero. But then then the side
effect of that is to increment the PC register
to one and then run that instruction. And so when
that instruction runs, we increment X. And so you
can see that X is now incremented to one. But then
once that's instruction is run then it moves to
the O2 instruction and that is also an increment
which it reads and then it increments X to two
and then it runs to the last instruction which is
a break and then that stops our program. So it's
uh it runs runs three instructions and then stops.
So, at this point, you might say to yourself, "Oh,
wait a second. This seems familiar." Clearing
a register and incrementing a register and then
stopping. That's something we've done before.
Literally, in previous lectures, you have built a
two instruction computer with a latch and an adder
and a clock. And so, you can say, "Oh, well, what
is this?" Well, the register is like the latch.
The the adder is the thing that does the increment
for us because the latch's output goes into the
adder and we've hard-coded a one to the other
input of the adder. And then we have a clock that
decides when things are going to run. And then we
have an instruction which is either zero or one.
This is a this is a one-bit computer, right?
And the thing that I complained about several
times in previous lectures is that it's not
reading instructions from memory. What we just got
done doing is reading instructions from memory.
And then there's the decode logic which is always
a difficult thing for students to understand where
it is looking at literally the bits of the
instruction and using and gates and or gates
actually enabling or disabling parts of the of the
processor. So, so the the increment instruction or
the the the loading into the latch based on the
clock is turned off based on the instruction. So,
the decoding and if you look at the decoding of a
typical typical microprocessor, it's like a whole
city block, right? And so the instructions in a
real computer sitting in memory, the decoding has
to look at all eight of those bits in our 6502 and
it has to send all those bits to various places to
turn on and off elements of the registers and
elements of the arithmetic logic unit. And so
we had it this is 8bit instructions which means
we have a whole bunch of things that we can do
and control. Now, if you think about it, at this
point, if you had enough time, you could build a
CDC 6504 and manufacturing capability because if
you go to that simple CPU and that simple CPU,
the latch, the adder, and the clock can be mapped
to transistors because underneath them they're
transistors. and we covered that. And then we
showed you how to make VLSI logic design where you
can lay out in a two-dimensional grid of different
materials that cause transistors, right? And then
all you would need is a billion-dollar personal
manufacturing facility to turn those transistor
layouts into chips. and then you could cut those
chips up and then you could manufacture a 6502.
Now the goal of this course is not for you to
go and build a $2 billion uh microprocessor
fabrication facility but to understand that really
you know the essence of the entire process to
build a complex CPU and produce it. It's possible
and you understand the basics of it. So up next,
we're just going to start going into more
detail of the entire machine language.